Guide to the Rose Pastor Stokes Papers TAM.053
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rose Pastor Stokes Papers
1905-1933
1913-1933
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1879-1933
Feinberg, Ann
TAM.053
3.25 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box.
Rose Pastor Stokes (1879-1933), born Rose Wieslander in Russian Poland, was a leading Jewish-American socialist, birth control advocate, and after the Russian revolution, a communist. Stokes helped organize garment workers in New York City, wrote for the Jewish Daily News, The Masses and other left periodicals, and was the author of several feminist plays. Stokes was married to wealthy socialist James Phelps Stokes from 1905-1925, married communist leader Jerome Isaac Romaine (also known as Victor J. Jerome) in 1927, and died of cancer in Berlin in 1933.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version; microfilm call number is Film R-7124, Reels 67-68.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ann Feinberg, 1973. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1973.001, 1973.004, and NPA.1997.001.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Throughout the early 20th century, Rose Pastor Stokes was an extremely controversial and widely publicized socialist and communist. She was born to Jewish parents, Jacob and Anna Wieslander, on 18 July 1879 in Russian Poland. After her parents' separation in 1882, her mother relocated in London's East Side and married a cigar maker named Israel Pastor, whose surname Rose took. Rose attended the Bell Lane Free School for only two years and then assisted her mother in making satin bows for slippers.
In 1890, the Pastors came to America and settled in Cleveland, Ohio. Because of the economic plight of her family Rose went to work, in a cigar factory. In July 1901, Rose responded to an advertisement in the Jewish Daily News requesting information from factory workers. The newspaper not only published her story, but Rose was invited to become a regular contributor. After her family moved to New York City in 1903, Rose worked as an assistant to the editor of the Jewish Daily News. Her responsibilities in this position included writing an advice column to young women in the newspaper's English section, writing sketches and human interest features about the East Side of New York, and submitting short verses and editorials.
In July 1903, Rose was sent to interview James Graham Phelps Stokes, a wealthy resident of the University Settlement House. Impressed by his dedication to socialism and reform, Rose became a close friend of Stokes and eventually the friendship turned to love. The couple married on July 18th 1905 and, after a European honeymoon, they rented an apartment near the University Settlement.
Although initially committed to settlement work, the Stokes' gradually turned their attention to socialist endeavors. In September 1905, James helped form the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, an organization dedicated to promoting the study of socialism among college students and faculty members. During the following year, James and Rose became members of the Socialist Party and worked diligently for various socialist activities and causes.
By 1912, James began to devote less of his time to socialism and more to research and writing. Rose, on the other hand, began to emerge as an effective socialist and labor leader. In May and June of 1912, Rose helped to lead a strike by the New York City restaurant and hotel workers and, in the winter of 1913, she aided the New York garment workers in their bitter strike. During this period, Rose also began to devote considerable time to writing proletarian plays and poetry. In 1916, she wrote The Women Who Wouldn't which was a play about the rise of a woman labor leader. Rose also contributed numerous poems and articles to such publications as The Masses, Independent, and Century.
Rose's artistic accomplishments did not detract from her social crusades. Foremost among Rose's causes at this time was her campaign in 1915 and 1916 to overturn the conviction of a labor leader, Patrick Quinlan, who had been arrested for his participation in the Paterson silk workers strike. Eventually, Rose and her supporters were able to overturn Quinlan's conviction. Another cause which occupied a considerable amount of Rose's time was the fight to distribute birth control information. While engaged in this campaign, Rose organized meetings for Margaret Sanger and Emma Goldman, both of whom were frequently arrested for lecturing on contraception.
When the United States entered World War I in April 1917, Rose and James were among those who withdrew from the Socialist Party because of its anti-war position. For James the separation from the Socialist Party was permanent, but Rose changed her mind after the Russian Revolution of 1917 and was readmitted to the party in February 1918. In March 1918, Rose was indicted under the Espionage Act for making the following statement to the Kansas City Women's Dining Club: "No government which is for the profiteers can be also for the people, and I am for the people, while the government is for the profiteers." On 1 June 1918, Rose was found guilty and sentenced to ten years in the Missouri State Penitentiary. In March 1920, an appeals court reversed her conviction and, in November 1921, the case was dismissed.
While her case was still pending in the courts, Rose became involved in the Socialist Party's "Left Wing Caucus" disputes. Obviously sympathetic with the left wing of the Michigan branch and the foreign language locals, Rose withdrew from the Socialist Party for the second time and became a founding member of the Communist Party. In 1922, Rose traveled to Moscow as an American delegate to the Fourth Congress of the Communist International. During these proceedings, Rose served as the reporter for the special Negro Commission. Upon her return to the United States, Rose was elected to serve on the Executive Committee of the newly formed Workers' Party. It was at this time that Rose adopted the pseudonym "Sasha".
Rose's marriage was jeopardized as a result of her activities with the communists. On 17 October 1925, James was granted an interlocutory decree of divorce, thus setting the two political opponents free to pursue their own careers. Two years later, Rose married Jerome Isaac Romaine (also known as Victor J. Jerome), a language teacher and an active communist. Following the marriage, Rose retained the name of Stokes and continued her controversial activities with the Communist Party. In 1930, Rose learned that she had cancer and thus retired to Westport, Connecticut. Upon learning about Rose's physical condition, many of her communist friends raised funds to send her to Europe for medical treatment. While being treated for the disease in a Frankfurt am Main municipal hospital, Rose Pastor Stokes died on 20 June 1933.
Scope and Contents
The Rose Pastor Stokes Papers, 1905-1933, consist of 44 subject files (some contain multiple folders) and several subfiles pertaining to Stokes' public and personal life. The subject files in this collection were established by Rose Pastor Stokes when she was preparing to write her autobiography. All of the items have been left in their original order except where another file was considered more appropriate for an item. Each of the subject files has been assigned a microfilm reel frame number and each of the sub-files have been assigned the same frame number as its major file and an alphabetical designation (i.e. XIX:15A, in which the roman numeral XIX indicates that the Stokes Papers are the 19th collection within the microfilm set titled Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library). A full citation for each of the subject files and sub-files can be found in the complete reel list for this collection.
This collection contains considerable correspondence in both the specific correspondence files and other subject files. The bulk of the correspondence was written from 1914 to 1918. In the Intercollegiate Socialist Society file (1), there are approximately 60 letters, including those from Harry W. Laidler, James Graham Phelps Stokes, and Rose Pastor Stokes. The subject file pertaining to birth control and the National Birth Control League (7) contains approximately 141 letters, many of which are from women asking for birth control information. Some of the principal correspondents in this file are Margaret Sanger, Ben Reitman, and Leonard D. Abbott.
There is correspondence in this collection relating to various members of the Stokes family (13a-13c). Included in these sub-files are letters from Rose Pastor Stokes; James Graham Phelps Stokes; Anna Pastor (her mother); Bernard, Cecil, and Maurice Pastor (her half-brothers); Lillian Pastor (her half-sister); Anson Phelps Stokes (her brother-in-law); Caroline Stokes; Helen Phelps Stokes (her sister-in-law); William Earl Dodge Stokes; and William Pletcher (Lillian Pastor's husband).
The largest quantity of correspondence in this collection is located in the chronological correspondence file (frame XIX:15), which contains letters from Eugene V. Debs, Max Eastman, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Kahlil Gibran (see also frame 38), Charlotte Perkins Gilman, Emma Goldman, Victor J. Jerome, Harry W. Laidler, Scott Nearing, Margaret Sanger, Upton Sinclair, Lincoln Steffens, Rose Strunsky, Horace Traubel, Anna Strunsky Walling, and William English Walling. Following are undated correspondence (frame XIX:15A), arranged in alphabetical order by the last name of the author of the letter. Some of the major correspondents in this sub-file include Harry W. Laidler, Walter Lippmann, Scott Nearing, Ida Rauh, Rose Strunsky, and Horace Traubel. The undated and unidentified correspondence (frame XIX:15B) contains only 15 letters. There are also separate correspondence folders relating to such individuals as Olive Telford Dargan (frame XIX:15D), Ann (Kaplan) Williams Feinberg (frame XIX:15E), Lincoln Steffens and Daniel Kiefer (frame XIX:15F), and J. Edward Morgan (frame XIX:15G).
Another significant amount of correspondence is located in the subject files relating to the Patrick Quinlan case (frame XIX:22-22b). Some of the major correspondents in these files are Patrick Quinlan, Rose Pastor Stokes, Walter Lippmann, Morris Hillquit, and Elizabeth Gurley Flynn.
Among the writings of Rose Pastor Stokes in this collection are the following: a manuscript of a play jointly written by Rose Pastor Stokes and Alice Blache, entitled, Shall the Parents Decide? (frame XIX:4); a few pages from Rose's autobiography (frame XIX:6); several short articles on the Patrick Quinlan case (frame XIX:22); two poems (frame XIX:23); three sketches about Russia based on Rose's observations as an American delegate to the Fourth Congress of the Communist International in Moscow (frame XIX:24); and a five page essay concerning prison conditions (frame XIX:42).
Virtually all of the subject files and sub-files in this collection include numerous newspaper clippings. The clippings are arranged in chronological order within each file and sub-file. It should also be. emphasized that the newspaper clippings always precede other items within each file and dub-file.
Frame XIX:6A consists of reproductions of 11 photographs which have been arranged in chronological order and include both portraits of Rose Pastor Stokes -and group photographs of prominent socialists. In the lower right-hand corner of each photograph is a number that corresponds with the description of that particular ­photograph in the complete reel list.
The only items which were not filmed in the Rose Pastor Stokes Papers were: three photographs of Rose Pastor Stokes, two newspaper clippings relating to woman's suffrage, two copyrighted publications concerning marriage, and one newspaper clip­ping pertaining to lynching.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by topic.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM 110 Olive Tilford Dargan Papers (Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes)
Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: A Guide to the Microfilm Edition / edited by Thomas C. Pardo. Sanford, N.C.: Microfilming Corp. of America, c1979. 181 p.
Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956 (Film R-7124)
Black-and-white photographs.; Communism -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Silk Workers' Strike, Paterson, N.J., 1913.; Correspondence.; Birth control -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.; Abbot, Leonard Dalton, 1878-1953; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Gilman, Charlotte Perkins, 1860-1935; Walling, Anna Strunsky, 1879-; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933; Intercollegiate Socialist Society (U.S.); Nearing, Scott, 1883-1983.; National Birth Control League; Masses (New York, N.Y.); Quinlan, Patrick L.; Romaine, Jerome I. (Victor J. Jerome); Steffens, Lincoln, 1866-1936.; Stokes, James Graham Phelps, 1872-1960; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Strunsky, Rose; Washington Square Players (New York, N.Y.); Woman's Peace Party; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Reitman, Ben L. (Ben Lewis), 1879-1942.; Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1879-1933; Feinberg, Ann
- Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1913-1924, undated; 133561 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 1
- Hotel and Waiters Strike, 1912; 133560 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 2
- Health, Jun 17, 1930-Dec 28, 1932; 133559 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 3
- Manuscripts, Contents Shall the Parents Decide? By RPS and Alice Blache. 47 pp. undated. (A play about birth control) Typescript, 133558 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 4
- Miscellaneous, 1909-1933; 133557 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 5
- Bills and Receipts, 1913-1918; 133556 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hotel and Waiters Strike, 1912; 133555 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Biography, 1905-1933, undated; 133554 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 6
- Photographs 1. John Martin's Camp at "Summerbrook" in the Adirondacks, People are unidentified. 1904? 2. John Martin's Camp in the Adirondacks, Man at the right is Upton Sinclair and the man in the center is J. G. P. Stokes. Summer 1907. 3. At Summerbrooke; Rose Pastor Stokes, John Martin and Prestonia Mann Martin. [Not microfilmed] 3A. Socialist convention in Baltimore. People are unidentified. 1916? 4. Rose Pastor Stokes, nd. 5. Rose Pastor Stokes, in her wedding dress, accompanied by members of the Stokes family, nd. 6. L-R Bernard Pastor, LeRoy Scott, Miriam Finn Scott, Alexander Irvine, nd. 7. J. Alonzo King, Caritos Island, nd. 8. L-R J. G. P. Stokes, unidentified, Rufus Weeks, Edward Slosson, unidentified, John Corbin?, Prof W. Noyes, nd. 9. L-R Unidentified, J. G. P. Stokes, John Corbin?, unidentified, Edward Slosson, Rufus Weeks, unidentified, nd., 10. Unidentified man, nd. 11. L-R Henri LaFontaine, Mrs. LaFontaine, Charlotte Perkins Gilman, Houghton Gilman, nd 12. J.G.P. Stokes?, Rose Pastor Stokes?, unidentified [not microfilmed] 13. Unidentified portrait [not microfilmed], circa 1904-1916, undated; 133553 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Birth Control, 1913-1931, undated; 133552 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 7
- Art, Jul 1913; 133551 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 8
- Politics, Mar 16, 1915-Jul 21, 1924; 133550 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 9
- Socialist Party, 1905-1918; 133549 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 10
- Charity, 1913-1914; 133548 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 11
- Humor, 1915; 133547 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 12
- Letters from Rose Pastor Stokes to J. G. P. Stokes, Apr 26, 1905-Mar 20, 1918; 133546 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 13
- Letters from J. G. P. Stokes to Rose Pastor Stokes, Feb 9, 1914-Nov 6, 1924; 133545 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Stokes Family, 1905-1915; 133544 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Economics, 1914; 133543 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 14
- Correspondence, 1905-1912; 133542 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Film R-7124, Reel 67: Frame XIX: 15
- Correspondence, 1913; 133541 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, Jan 1914-Jun 1914; 133540 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, Jul 1914-Dec 1914; 133539 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1915; 133538 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Jan 1916-Jun 1916; 133537 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15
- Correspondence, Jul 1916-Dec 1916; 133536 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1917; 133535 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1918; 133534 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1919; 133533 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1920; 133532 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1921; 133531 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1922; 133530 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1923-1927; 133529 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1928-1933; 133528 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Alphabetical, A - J, undated; 133527 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15A
- Correspondence, Alphabetical, K - Z, undated; 133526 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, undated; 133525 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15B
- Telegrams, undated; 133524 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15C
- Letters from Olive Tilford Dargan, See also TAM 110 Olive Tilford Dargan Papers (Letters to Rose Pastor Stokes), Apr 16, 1914-1924; 133523 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15D
- Letters from Rose Pastor Stokes to Ann (Kaplan) Williams, May 8, 1931-Jun 10, 1933; 133522 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15E
- Letters from Lincoln Steffens and Daniel Kiefer, Dec 28, 1919-Feb 23, 1933; 133521 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15F
- Correspondence with J. Edward Morgan, nd Box 5, 1905-1924, undated; 133520 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 15G
- Socialism, 1907-1924, undated; 133519 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 16
- Industrial Workers of the World, 1913, 1918; 133518 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 17
- Unemployment, 1913-1915; 133517 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 18
- Garment Workers' Strikes, 1907-1915, undated; 133516 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 19
- Crime, 1913-1914, undated; 133515 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 20
- Education, 1913; 133514 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 21
- Patrick Quinlan-Defense, 1914-1916, undated; 133513 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 22
- William Z. Foster, 1923-1924, undated; 133512 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 22A
- Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, 1913-1918, undated; 133511 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 22B
- Poetry, 1912-1916, undated; 133510 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 23
- Soviet Union/Russia, 1911-1922, undated; 133509 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 24
- War, 1914-1917, undated; 133508 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 25
- Prohibition, 1914, 1916; 133507 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 26
- Industrial Efficiency and Conditions, 1909-1914; 133506 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 27
- Social Work, 1913; 133505 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 28
- Revolution, 1914, 1920; 133504 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 29
- Religion, 1913-1916; 133503 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 30
- Drama and Music, 1913-1920, undated; 133502 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 31
- Woman's Independence, 1916-1924; 133501 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 32
- Marriage, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Peace, 1916-1917, undated; 133500 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 33
- Agitation, 1916, 1924; 133499 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 34
- Negroes, 1908; 133498 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 35
- Lynching, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Children, 1914, 1924; 133497 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 36
- Publication, 1909-1931, undated; 133496 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 37
- Resnikoff, 1916-1920, undated; 133495 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 38
- Literature, 1913, 1917; 133494 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 39
- Child Labor, 1916; 133493 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 40
- Upper Class, 1906; 133492 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 41
- Prison, 1912; 133491 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 42
- Labor Conditions, 1913; 133490 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX: 43
- Civics, 1917, undated; 133489 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Film R-7124, Reel 68: Frame XIX:
- Clippings, Intercollegiate Socialist Society, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Clippings, Health, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Clippings, Hotel/Waiters Strikes, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
- Clippings, Biography, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Clippings, Birth Control, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Clippings, Art, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Clippings, Socialist Party, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Original Newspaper Clippings, circa 1908-1931 (Box 6, Folder 14-24, Box 7, Folder 1-14)